SOHYEON HWANG

sohyeonhwang.com sohyeonhwang@u.northwestern.edu Updated: 6 Oct 2022

RESEARCH **INTERESTS**

(self-)governance, organization, scale, polycentricity + pluralism + heterogeneity, social computing, computational social science, interviews;

I study (1) how groups on social computing platforms govern in community-specific ways, and (2) the subsequent downstream implications. I analyze the development and implementation of heterogeneous governing routines across online spaces, examining rules, tools, and design using large-scale data. In parallel, I conduct interview studies to elicit individuals' experiences of variation, to understand the practical implications of heterogeneity at scale. I also use computational methods to study how information may take on multiple meanings. My goal is to understand how we can foster accountability, autonomy, and collaboration at the nexus of technology and society via distributed logics of governance.

EDUCATION

Northwestern University, Evanston, IL

2019-Present

MA/PhD in Media, Technology, and Society

Advisor: Aaron Shaw

2021, MA thesis: Parallel evolutions of peer-produced online governance

2024, Doctoral dissertation expected

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

2014-2018

BA in Government and in Information Science cum laude, with distinction in all subjects

AFFILIATIONS

Community Data Science Collective

2019-Present

PhD Student (funded by **NSF GRFP**) PIs: Aaron Shaw, Benjamin Mako Hill

Relevant grants: NSF IIS-1617468, NSF IIS-1910202

Lab on Innovation, Networks, and Knowledge

2020-Present

Affiliate PhD Student Researcher

PIs: Emőke-Ágnes Horvát

Relevant grants: NSF IIS-2133963, NSF IIS-2133964

PUBLICATIONS Peer-reviewed, archival

Hwang, Sohyeon, Emőke-Ágnes Horvát, and Daniel Romero. Forthcoming 2023. "Information retention in the multi-platform discussions of science". In Proc. 17th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM2023). Cyprus. [arXiv]

Hwang, Sohyeon and Aaron Shaw. 2022. "Rules and rule-making in the five largest Wikipedias". In Proc. 16th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM2022), Vol. 16, pp. 347-357. Atlanta, Georgia. [link]

Hwang, Sohyeon and Jeremy Foote. 2021. "Why do people participate in small online communities?" Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 5, CSCW2, Article 462 (October 2021), 25 pages.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3479606 [recording]

Best Paper Honorable Mention

Under peer review

Pre-prints available upon request.

Hwang, Sohyeon, Charles Kiene, Serene Ong, and Aaron Shaw. "Curating bot stacks: Third-party applications and online community governance".

Book chapters

Foote, Jeremy and Sohyeon Hwang. "Online communities and big data" in *Group Communication: An Advanced Introduction* (eds. Torsten Reimer, Ernest Park, Joseph Bonito), *forthcoming* in 2023.

Posters and extended abstracts (non-archival)

Hwang, Sohyeon, Emőke-Ágnes Horvát, and Daniel Romero. 2022, multiple venues. "Information retention in multi-platform discussions of science".

- Poster presentation at International Conference on Computational Social Science (IC²S²) 2022, 19-22 July 2022. Chicago, IL. (Presented by Sohyeon Hwang.) [pdf].
- Poster presentation at International Conference on the Science of Science and Innovation (ICSSI) 2022. June 7-9, 2022. Washington DC, USA. (Presented by Daniel Romero.)

Hwang, Sohyeon and Aaron Shaw. 2020. "Heterogeneous practices in collective governance". *Collective Intelligence* 2020 (CI 2020). Boston & Copenhagen (Virtually held due to COVID-19). [pdf] [recording].

Rahm, Brian G., Sohyeon Hwang, Tim Joo, Karin Teuffer, Sridhar Vedachalam, Deb Grantham, and Susan J. Riha. 2016. "Making the case for OWTS management: lessons from case studies and research." In *AGU Fall 2016 Meeting Abstracts*. San Francisco, California. [pdf].

AWARDS Fellowships + Scholarships

2020-2023. National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship, value 134,000 USD.

2018. Emma Bowen Foundation Fellowship (Democracy Fund), value 6,000 USD.

2017. Telluride House Scholarship (Cornell Branch), 2017-2018 residential scholarship.

2017. Frederic Conger Wood Research Fellowship, value: 3,500 USD.

2014. Bio-Rad Laboratories Scholarship, value: 1,000 USD.

2014. National Merit Scholarship (top <1%), value: 1,000 USD.

Recognitions + Honors

2022. Outstanding Review, Special Recognition, CSCW 2022.

2021. Best Paper Honorable Mention, CSCW 2021.

2018. Excellence in Research Award, Information Science Dept., Cornell University.

2014-2018. Dean's List for Excellence in Scholarship, Cornell University.

2017. Class of 2018 Award, Class Councils Cornell.

2015. Academic Excellence in German, the German Consulate General New York.

Grants + Miscellaneous Funding

2022. Quantitative methods training funding, MTS/Northwestern, value 500 USD.

• For the Workshop on Research Design for Causal Inference, Northwestern Law School (8/2022).

ORGANIZED WORKSHOPS

Li, Hanlin, Leah Ajmani, Moyan Zhou, Nicholas Vincent, Sohyeon Hwang, Tiziano Piccardi, Sneha Narayan, Sherae Daniel. "Ethical Tensions, Norms, and Directions in the Extraction of Online Volunteer Work". Companion Publication of the 2022 Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing. 2022. [site]

PUBLIC SPEAKING + SCHOLARSHIP

"Learning from small and overlapping communities". Science of Community Dialogues, by the Community Data Science Collective. 11 February 2022. Virtual.

Discord Moderator Discord Academic Talks (DMDAT). 13 January 2022. Virtual Q&A.

The science of social media. Uncontrolled Variables: A Science & Comedy Show, 2 September 2021. Lincoln Lodge Theater, Chicago, IL.

"South Korea's dud(?) democracy: The candlelight protests in context". Cornell Branch of the Telluride Association – House PubSpeaks, February 2018. Ithaca, NY.

Web

Interview series loosely centered around research + technology, media, and social behavior:

• "From scientific management to data-driven labor organizing". Interview with Dr. Vera Khovanskaya, NSF/CRA/CCC Computing Innovation Postdoctoral Fellow at UC San Diego (recorded 06/2022, published 08/2022)

INVITED TALKS

"Lessons on decentralized governance from online communities". Governance Learning Forum 2022, Other Internet. 18-19 August 2022. Virtual.

"Why do people participate in small online communities?". COM 481: Online Communities (taught by Dr. Benjamin Mako Hill), University of Washington. 2 March 2022. Virtual.

"Governance of and by (and within) platforms". COMM ST 378: Online Communities and Crowds (taught by Dr. Aaron Shaw), Northwestern University. 9 February 2022. Evanston, IL.

"Why do people participate in small online communities?". HCI seminar series, University of Washington, 5 November 2021, Virtual,

Invited panels

"Content moderation on Discord" D/ARC (Discord Academic Research Community) - Bonfire Chat. 18 May 2022. Virtual.

• Panel, hosted by Hibby Thach: Robyn Caplan, Joseph Seering, Zac Parker, Sohyeon Hwang

WORK

Reveal from the Center for Investigative Reporting

2018

EXPERIENCE

Emma Bowen Foundation Fellow, Audience Team

Center for the Study of Economy & Society, Cornell University

2016-2018

Undergraduate Assistant under Dr. Victor Nee

Tompkins County - Cornell Cooperative Extension

2016

Communications & Outreach Intern

New York State Water Resources Institute, Cornell University

2015

Summer Undergraduate Intern under Dr. Brian Rahm.

TEACHING

Research supervision

Emily Zou (undergraduate research assistant (RA), Northwestern University, Spring 2022 - Present)

Serene Ong (undergraduate RA, Northwestern University, Spring 2021 – Present)

Daryn McElroy (undergraduate RA, Northwestern University, Spring - Fall 2021)

Amanda Hardy (Master's RA, University of Michigan, Winter/Spring 2021)

Ellie Coleman (undergraduate RA, Northwestern University, Summer 2020)

Courses

COMM ST 378: Online Communities and Crowds. Graduate Teaching Assistant (discussion section instructor of record), under Aaron Shaw. Northwestern University. 2022, Winter.

COMM ST 159: Computing Everywhere. Graduate student instructor, under Jeremy Birnholtz. Northwestern University. Multiple quarters.

- 2022, Spring. How NLP breaks down (your) text into data.
- 2022, Winter. Using APIs to gather online information.
- 2021, Spring. Using APIs to gather online information.

INFO 4240: Designing Technologies for Social Impact. Undergraduate teaching assistant, under Phoebe Sengers. Cornell University. 2016, Fall. 2017, Fall.

Training and certification

Reflective and Effective Teaching Program, Northwestern University, 2022-2023. Inclusive Teaching Practicum, Northwestern University, November 2021.

REVIEWING Conferences: AOIR, ICA, CSCW, ICWSM

SERVICE HCI+D PhD book club, Co-founder/organizer. Summer 2020 – present.

Metagov Seminar, seminar planning committee member. 2020-2022.

Human-Computer Interaction Events Committee, Northwestern University. 2020-2021.

Research retreat co-organizer, Community Data Science Collective, Fall 2019. Cornell Branch of the Telluride House, Speaker Series Co-organizer, 2017-2018.

Professional association membership

Association for Computing Machinery International Communication Association Association of Internet Researchers

Non-academic service

GirlForward, Math Tutor, 2019-2021.